so welcome everyone from the magnets team and um
thanks for joining us today uh we would like to
welcome giannini roger carmo from university of
sao paulo and she's going to present a talk with
the title palamunity record of spell attempts from
northa africa thank you jenny the flores is yours
can you see that works fine thank you okay so hi
uh first i'd like to thank you for an invitation
and say that i'm very excited to be here uh
thank you everyone for watching and everyone who
will watch this recording lately today
i'm going to talk about the phenomena
magnetic record of spirituals in north africa
but more specifically i'm going to talk about
fast variations in uh in the geomagnetic field and
how spirituals can help us to understand them so
no no no no okay okay uh
so this presentation will focus on levantine
iron age anomaly which is called responsibility
oh i'm sorry oh sorry sorry go ahead sorry which
correspond uh to extremely high german geomagnetic
field intensive record in eastern europe
and mid-east and different from the
south america anomaly that it's observed
today uh the levantine anomaly it's
only studied through paleomagnetic data
and does not have occurrence nowadays
so here is the first two steps for just for
here is the uh two first step works to report
this anomaly and in the 11 11 and normally two
peaks in the geomagnetic field uh is occurring
one and at nine eight another and seven
forty uh years before the common era and
it's these days these aids were uh better
uh determined by shore at all in 2016.
and the anomaly generation mechanisms
are still unknown so determination
of time tastes and specials extent it's
important to understand what caused it
in this way it would be possible to know about
more about the time dynamics of the outer core
so uh here we present um where it is anomalous
better define it so in this east portion from
europe uh there are also a number of works that
can restrict this extinction in the northwest of
this anomaly but uh the western limits on africa
it's poorly determined so here we have few datas
and uh in the canary islands canard island
we have there are studies reporting a high
palatalistic spike however this spike's not so
well defined uh there may be a difference of 1500
years between the region of the anomaly
and its appearance in connor islands so
in this work they evaluate the intensity of the
geomagnetic field over time and try to map this
western rift movement but the lack of
parliament that palu magnetic data on
africa content does not allow them to
understand how the anomaly is start and
canary islands so the poor spatial and corporal
distribution of data from north africa creates
difficulties to understand behavior of the
anomaly in this region and to understand it
we need a large volume of paleomagnetic
data covering the period of the anomaly
so to help with this discussion we use uh the
record of a set of skeletons from morocco composed
by uh three stalagmites collected in the winting
dawn cave near to the kind of canary islands so
uh here is 11th region and the kenner island and
and why do we use philippines so how can spirit
teams help us to understand fast field variations
first spirit tents are crystalline the post
formed in case as a result of precipitation
from supersaturated solutions and experitems of
calcium carbonate or calcite are the most common
here you can observe some kinds of spirituals
here we have some stalagmites stalactites columns
behind this box we have
curtains so you you when we
do uh value magnet studies usually you
we work with stalagmites or float stones
that be this huge uh amount of uh carbonate so um
so and now how speed attempts
can record the geomagnetic field
in a simple way there is a
production of magnetite uh
in the soil above the cave the
soil rich in magnetic minerals
is transported by water into the cave through
the faults and fissures uh in the bedroom these
minerals are then the posters of the surface of
this uh spirituals through the dripping water
another way to have the triple material inside the
caves is do the fluid events or wind actions and
these events bring allogeneic material into into
the cave so during the percolation of the water
in the caves the bedrock dissolves and solution is
enriched in carbonate so stalagmites are forming
by dripping warden ripping by dripping
a super saturated solution solution of
calcium carbonate these droplets bring with them
the tritone material from the soil above the cave
and these materials rich and magnetic magnetic
minerals that can record the magnetic field
when these minerals are blocked between the
calcite minerals they can report this uh this
good behavior um so this and some of minerals
that would form found in on spell attempts
and despite the low magnetic intensity
of stalagmites of spirit attempts so stag
mites can be used to obtain information about the
poly magnetic field and they have some important
advantages when you compare with other traditional
artists and panel magnetism so the locking time
it's long enough to allow the magnetic moments
to align but it's wrapped enough for a courageous
recording of digital magnetic field behavior uh
spin attempts are unaffected by post depositional
effects and can be dated with high accuracy it's
like uh if you think in the sea here's the layers
it's like a very small signature basin in
which each layer could be could provide an
annual information of the geomagnetic field but
it's not so easy each layer has few magnetic
minerals so it's necessary to measure a certain
volume to reach the resolution of magnetometers
uh here i show the marking of these samples
usually you pick the same of the samples their
center region of the stalagmites to avoid
secular effects effects calling for this uh
this is sloped so we avoid this these regions uh
here i show a different from the chronological
models that we have made from new urethral
data and use a stellar style h algorithm so
this sample win1 has few eights because the
this sample has lots of uh the triton content
and this this disturb uh the
technique to date the samples
so we use this sample just to define the
appropriate protocols the more appropriate
protocols and labor laboratory techniques
for parliament biomagnetic investigation
and after we did some everything after
we we did do some tests here when
applied the best techniques on the other samples
between 2 and 0.3 and when we look this uh age
models we see that we have some uh two equals
here uh and if we calculate the growth rating
we see that they have a slow rate growth
rating of 0.04 millimeters per year on average
so uh the specimens have an average
of five millimeters on height
and were prepared with a thin saw blade of
0.4 millimeters to avoid the loss of material
and here is our pilot sample pilot test
sample so our magnetic measurements
were performed here in brazil in the
sphenage using a squid magnetometer
we start with af degaussing
and so um and so that has this
rest of uh remnants yeah indicating that presence
of high positivity minerals so in blue we have our
blue we have our af treatment and yellow
it's the thermal treatment so uh we did the
thermal treatment the thermal demagnetization to
characterize this other magnetic carrier and the
the magnetization curves of nine percent
of the samples show this similar behavior
it's aggregate intensity decrease above 200
degrees and abrupt drop after six sixty degrees
uh and the total loss of the remedy is at six
eight degrees supporting a strong evidence
of presence of hematite so we call
we'll calculate both directions
of the af and thermal treatments and we
calculate and see that they are compatible
showing that the stalagmites has a root
boost uh repos reproducibility and that
the positional mechanism is reliable for the
determination of the test geomagnetic field
so uh we did some r i am curve acquisition curves
and these curves show the presence of magnetic
of two magnetic components
one with a higher positivity
uh do the hematite another with a lower point
specific that we interpreted as magnetite
but uh we still need to evaluate the
level of oxidation of this uh magnetite
so we have a mixture in this
in this set of uh stalagmites
and if we see the s rato it's possible for other
two samples win two and win three it's possible
to see that that the mixing of hematite
and magnetite along the whole experience
but without much variation
so we have mixture or pillars
but without a great uh variation
uh so after he did that test in win one uh
we applied the isaf the magnetization uh on
speedo teams win two and win three and we
have the same behavior of the win one so
our intensity starts to decrease and then remain a
part of this magnetization uh but we can see that
there are there are parts that it's really stable
we have really straight stable sino without
secular components the only specimen that show
a secular company is this wintry and this is
passing or discarded for from analysis because
it presents a higher value of angular deviation
and we and when we see this this uh this figure
we can see that we can see that uh levels with
higher concentration of the predictable
material has a higher intensities um
so both side needs has a
stable the stable components
uh here in this figure shows the
results that we obtained from wind two
and win three so we choose this
green spots and green three with red
and we are comparing with the geomagnetic
models so the geomagnetic models is those
is the first continuous
curves and here is uh our aids
so uh when you compare it this results with this
net modules from more further region of morocco
we can see that first our results
results are internally consistent and
and the directional data generate
agrees with the with the magnetic model
so here uh for declination we have a better
answer and inclination we have this this answer
and both and both data and declination
inclination match with the models
and we can see that both samples can record this
rapid variation fast variations on the geomagnetic
field including this appropriate changes in
direction for the last two years 2000 years
and here is the the future that uh that
we use so we apply a future for matt uh
15 degrees of men and all samples that has the
then value then value over the net values we cut
from this analysis as well because our compound
it's not going to the center of the sidewalk
and it would not represent the primary
uh direction of the magnetic field
so here we are comparing uh our directional data
with the the volcanic data from canada's islands
and morocco and we can see that have a good
correlation between the spell attempts and the
volcanic record and here in inclination
we have some ice carter interval here
but it's uh but there is a good correlation and
mainly in this first two thousand years here
um so to determine the relative values
that valentine's day we apply the episode
italian method on wing samples take care
take prepare to choose the same interval
in which we determine our characteristic
component so it's difficult to work with the
sample because we have this mystery of magnetite
and hematite we can see here in our right our plot
and we need to be careful when we do
finally tasted uh relative pancakes in this
kind of material so uh we did it's really
careful and when we compare our data with
models and in volcanic data we can
see first here when we see models
they are uh they have some difference they are
quite quite constant but they have some difference
by the intensity uh in intensive mode intensive
values and when we compare our our data with these
these models we see that our relative valentine's
results are in agreement with the geomagnetic
models mainly for the last 2 000 years however
there is a systematic difference here between
our data and the geomagnetic models and in this
interval between zero and a thousand uh years
before the commodore era this in this interval
comprise the levantine anomaly so this time
interval is also characterized by
characteristic by a strong dispersion
in the absolute valentine's
day from the canary islands
so when we compare
our data here
with segments from auburn island that's in the
south of spain this this blue start it's quite
near from our our spot uh we can see a
similar trend with low intensity values
so with low intensity balance
and and here is the the record of burn declination
inclination and intensity and here we have this
same triangle so um could it confirm that that
this region is out of 11 time anomaly influence uh
at the same time we had this trend uh we have this
noisy behavior with increase of the increase of
uh valentine's day value so it must be better
investigate and if we consider that this data
uh this data that we obtain and also this
data from overrun represents the reality so
maybe the geomagnetic models need
to be updated for this region and uh
and to be honest uh we need to interpret
more this this data for now and in summary
we have this for this work for now so we
have this magnetic mineralogy is interpreted
as a composed of magnetite and hematite along
the holy spirits and the remnant magnetization
in when one is stable for both magnetic carriers
the calculated directions are consistent for af
and the thermal analysis uh wind 2 and v3 records
are internally consistent and the directional data
generally agrees with the geomagnetic model and we
we can see it in the declination and inclination
uh data directions our relativity by intensity
shows a meaningful difference for intensity
between zero and uh thousand years before
the common era when it's compared with your
magnet models however it's has similar behavior to
segments from oberon uh this time interval is also
characterized by a strong dispersion in absolute
valentine's day from generic i fenris island so
could put be our region out for this for the
influence of this the levantine anomaly and
why we can see that higher intensities in canary
island so we need to answer this this question yet
so it's that thanks everyone thanks
for everyone that is watching
thank you very much jalini let's give a big
round of applause great happy skeletons there
okay thank you very much and now there is a
space for questions should anyone having some
you can use the chat if you
want and i can read them
up or you can ask i'll meet
yourself and ask the question
okay so i will read the question
there is in a chat by sayo
and so says hi janine a great presentation
sorry because i don't have a mic
just a curiosity have you compared your airplay
rpi with the shock iron age model this model
is focused on the study the eleventh and region
already incorporating new data from liberia thanks
uh it's that next step i need to compare and i'm
i want to i want to see if there's some different
behavior with different models
so it's it's a great tip
thanks yeah it's obviously a work in progress but
there's a lot of work already
done yeah thank you thanks
any other questions from the audience
kathy as a question uh yes please go ahead kathy
yeah thanks uh very interesting results janine
thanks for sharing them i'm uh wondering whether
you have any ideas about uh differences in the
uh rock magnetic properties in the interval
where you have this disagreement with the model
or whether you think that there could in fact
be some sort of um i i know that in stereo
themes we hope that we're going to get a very
detailed uh uh record in time i'm wondering if
there's something that could be uh smoothing
that out or disturbing it in that interval
so i didn't get all the questions sorry if
there is a correlation between your rock magnets
properties and the the region where there is the
disagreement within the models and uh when we did
this and and then it's it's like it's the when we
have these variations in our and in the magnetic
directions or we we have this problem and
then pallet and relative pen intensity it's
the most stable uh sign in the hour speed attempt
there's less and changing so i need to i need to
analyze this better to bring to you this this this
question but there's no correlation okay thank you
thank you any other questions
i don't don't see anyone
raising their hand or they
okay then i don't know another minute if somebody
wants to take the courage and ask ask other
questions well maybe i'll just make a comment i
think it's really kind of puzzling that we don't
you don't see a record of this high field strength
in this region because you'd expect if this was a
signal that was coming from the earth's core
you would expect it to have a pretty broad
regional extent so you wouldn't really expect
that you would see this it seems like you see
a low in the field strength there which um which
is also what you see in the the spanish settlement
so there's really a a bit of a puzzle there
that needs to be uncovered about the differences
thanks uh cathy for the comments
maybe additional magnetic measurements
can help but then of course it's
also relatively intensity so
it's hard to calibrate it then
to more of a absolute value
and yeah thanks again um
andrei you have a question yeah
thank you jenny it was very
illuminating talk but well i was
sort of uncertain whether to ask this or
not and but still what is your idea of
where hematite comes from to your
spelling terms is it is that brought for
from
from the surface together with magnetite
or its font and see it what do you think
uh to be honest i'd like to have part
of the the main carbon at the bedrock
to did some measurements and compare and i
didn't have this kind of sample so for now
i i don't know i need to get someone to
collect collected the sample for me yeah great
because you see the reason the
reason was that uh your s ratio is
your s ratio is very very stable along the record
along this pellet term that means that the ratio
the volumetric ratio of the two minerals
is also fairly stable and i really can't
can't quite
that should be so quite a climb just
how that's the question that i would
ask my sorry maybe it was my connection
that uh broke a little bit oh i don't know
oh okay anyway let it be let it be
that way yeah okay thank you yeah no i
i don't know if it's my connection maybe you
can type the question sorry well i say i think
you asked if then you will work more with
this data well that that will come by itself
uh the question is uh the question yeah and
anita there is another there is another
question in the chat could you read this
oh yes thank you sorry i didn't see my
connection is is quite bad i apologize
thank you andre thank you very much so uh danny
okay dennis kent is asking question hi af and
thermal demonization are not independent
with the magnetite and hematite carriers
until the magnesium temperature above 580
degrees centigrade are the directions above
580 centigrade different than lower
temperature or af direction thanks to dennis
sorry did was it too clear jenny okay uh yeah
uh to be honest first and that magnetic uh
my my first analysis was to apply af and in the
same sample we put in the the did the thermal
treatment and so i didn't do the thermal treatment
to the magnetized magnetite whereas the dematite
but when we compare just this sign for
hematite with that we have an af treatment
they are the same they are compact they
are not the same but they are current
so i don't know if that i answered this
question but i think yes yeah thank you
okay uh i think uh i think we had enough a
good discussion and um if you could unshare
your screen and and we can all give
another round of applause to janine
okay um all right so let me share my screen sorry
so thanks again gennini for your presentation
i would like to remind you that our next two
webinars are the fourth of may with sunny panopsky
and then the 18th of may uh with win williams
and then we are going to have a break for the egu
online in the end of may and more more magnets to
come and more speakers are welcome and we would
like to remind you that this recording then
will be made available on the youtube channel
so thank you very much again for
coming and we hope to see you next time